Guide to the Oregon Hops and Brewing Archives Oral History Collection 2014-2017
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections and Archives Research Center
- Interviews, 2014; Series 1
  - Townsend, Shaun, November 3, 2014
    Dr. Shaun Townsend is a senior researcher in hop breeding and genetics at Oregon State. In this interview, he discusses growing up in central Illinois, his education and research experience in agronomy at Montana State and New Mexico state, and how he came to work at Oregon State University in the hop program. He describes his passion for research in crop science, and how his career has fulfilled that. In addition, he discusses the transformation of the OSU hop breeding program to fit the needs for variety in the craft brewing industry and how he collaborates with local growers and brewers to produce optimal varieties. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on November 3, 2014 in the OSU Valley Library in Corvallis, Oregon.
  - Sage, Matt, November 11, 2014
    Matt Sage is a craft brewer, vintner and hop consultant whose work has contributed to the creation and expansion of many small businesses across the Pacific Northwest. In this interview, Sage discusses his wine and beer brewing ventures, detailing the operations and company culture of businesses like Associated Vintners, BridgePort Brewing Company, Rock Bottom Restaurant & Brewery, Cameron Winery, and finally, Indie Hops (the position he held at the time of the interview). Sage focuses heavily on the production and use of beer ingredients, as well as contemporary market trends of the hop industry. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton at the Indie Hops offices in Portland, Oregon on November 11, 2014.
  - Haunold, Alfred, November 18, 2014
    Dr. Haunold released the superstar hop varieties like Cascade, Willamette, Sterling, Liberty, Mt. Hood, and Santiam while he was with the USDA/ARS in Corvallis. During this interview he tells the story of the different hops he worked with, adding interesting details about people's personalities and technological advances. This interview was conducted by Shaun Townsend and Tiah Edmunson-Morton in Corvallis, Oregon on November 18, 2014.
- Interviews, 2015; Series 2
  - Wyatt, Susan and Gary, February 18, 2015
    Gary and Susan Wyatt are the founders and owners of Tumalo Hops, a farm often regarded as the first of its kind in Central Oregon. After the economic downturn of the early 2000s, the Wyatts chose to utilize five acres of their land to grow hops, planting, cultivating, and harvesting everything by hand. In this interview, the Wyatts recount the recent economic and cultural changes of Bend, as well as the importance of capitalizing on locality when selling their product to craft and homebrewers. The Wyatts also address the growing trend of agro-tourism and the desire to stay successful yet small via the pooling of intellectual and tangible resources. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton and Miles Wilhelm on February 18, 2015 at the couple’s farm in Tumalo, Oregon.
  - Bowman, Fred, March 11, 2015
    Fred Bowman is the former owner and co-founder of Portland Brewing Company, one of Oregon's first post-Prohibition micro breweries. In this interview, Bowman discusses the biological and mechanical skills and interests that led him to found a brewery in Portland with Jim Goodwin and Art Larrance in 1986. Bowman talks at length about his life before Portland Brewing Co., detailing an extensive trip to Europe, his enlistment in the Army Reserves, and a 16-year stint working for a Volkswagen distributor. Bowman also discusses the challenges surrounding Portland Brewing Company's first years of operation, as well as his eventual decision to branch off as an independent consultant. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton at Bowman's home in Portland, Oregon.
  - Firmat, Irene, May 4, 2015
    Irene Firmat is the founder and CEO of Full Sail Brewing Company, located in Hood River, Oregon. In this interview, she recalls her childhood as a Cuban immigrant in New York and the changes that brought her to Oregon as a buyer for department store Meier & Frank. Firmat also recounts the creation of Full Sail Brewing (originally known as Hood River Brewing) and the process of crafting a company culture of mutual respect and collaboration. In addition, Firmat discusses former and projected market trends of the craft beer industry, emphasizing her desire to witness a return to the quality-driven production of Portland’s flagship breweries of the 1980s. This interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on May 4, 2015 at the Full Sail Brewery in Hood River, Oregon.
  - Hoerner Rich, Joy, May 20, 2015
    The daughter of OSU hops specialist G.R. Hoerner, Joy Hoerner Rich graduated from OSU in the 1940s with a degree in Home Economics. In this interview, Hoerner Rich describes the atmosphere of campus and the Corvallis area during World War II, emphasizing the influences of the draft and the proximity of Camp Adair. After graduation, Hoerner Rich and her husband moved to Roseburg, Oregon, where she spent several decades as a kindergarten teacher and early childhood education expert. Hoerner Rich also details the work habits and duties of her father during his time at OSU and Kasetsart University in Bangkok, Thailand. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on May 20, 2015 at Hoerner Rich’s residence in Roseburg, Oregon.
  - Sidor, Larry, November 6, 2015
    Larry Sidor is the founder and brewmaster of Crux Fermentation Project, a brewery and tasting room in Bend, Oregon. A graduate of Oregon State University, Sidor allowed practicality to push him toward the food sciences—a decision which ultimately led to a prolonged passion for making wine and beer. In this interview, Sidor discusses the company culture and economic trends of his former places of employment: Olympia Brewing, hop merchant SS Steiner, and Deschutes Brewing. He stresses the need for trust and relationships in both the macro- and microbrewery settings, emphasizing the importance of maintaining a “farm to table mentality.” The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton and Chris Peterson on November 6, 2015 in Corvallis, Oregon. This interview has also been described in the Oregon State University Sesquicentennial Oral History Collection (OH 026).
  - Edgerton, Jeff, November 18, 2015
    Jeff Edgerton has been the master brewer at BridgePort Brewing Company since 2010. In this interview, he recounts his path from Blitz-Weinhard lab technician to BridgePort quality assurance manager and brewmaster. After earning a degree in microbiology at Oregon State University, Edgerton brought the practices of quality and consistency he learned at Blitz-Weinhard to the increasingly popular BridgePort Brewing in 1998. Edgerton explains the brewing industry as a “lifestyle career,” one which encouraged him to pursue further involvement with the Master Brewers Association and collaborate with OSU’s Fermentation Science students. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on November 18, 2015 at BridgePort Brewing in Portland, Oregon. This interview has also been described in the Oregon State University Sesquicentennial Oral History Collection (OH 026).
  - Flanagan, Mick, November 18, 2016
    Mick Flanagan, a mechanic at BridgePort Brewing Company, has worked for the brewery since 1989. The interview was conducted at the BridgePort Brewing Company in Portland on November 18, 2016 by Tiah Edmunson-Morton.
  - Harris, John, December 9, 2015
    Born and raised in Portland, brewer John Harris has worked in Oregon's oldest craft breweries. He was a brewer at McMenamins' Hillsdale Brewery & Public House and Cornelius Pass Roadhouse (1986-1988), was the first employee and head brewer at Deschutes Brewery in Bend (1988-1992), and ran the Full Sail South Waterfront Brewery in Portland (1992-2012) before opening Ecliptic Brewing in North Portland in 2013. In this interview Harris talks about growing up in Portland, attending Portland State University as a theater major, and working in the evolving craft industry for 30 years. This interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on December 9, 2015 at Ecliptic Brewery, 825 N Cook St in Portland, Oregon. This interview is not avaialble online.
- Interviews, 2016; Series 3
  - Annen, John, February 10, 2016
    Oral history interview with John Annen, fourth generation hop grower in Mount Angel, Oregon. Annen talks about the farming history of his family, the hop growing community in Oregon and the Oregon Hop Commission, mechanization of harvesting and processing practices, labor, diversification of the hops varieties grown, and working with macro and craft brewers. The interview was conducted at the Annen Farm in Mount Angel on February 10, 2016 by Tiah Edmunson-Morton. Also present was Nancy Sites, administrator for the Oregon Hop Commission.
  - Garves, Dana, February 19, 2016
    Dana Garves is a brewing chemist who owns and operates BrewLab, a company that provides chemical analyses for breweries, cideries, meaderies, and home brewers. In this interview, Garves talks about her early interest in studying Chemistry, her experiences attending the University of Oregon, her interest in STEM education for girls, her work at Ninkasi, and her decision to start her own company. Garves also talks at length about the Ninkasi Space Launch, a year long project that she was involved with as a chemist. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on February 19, 2016 at Garves' lab in Eugene.
  - Crabb, Chris, June 2, 2016
    Chris Crabb is the public relations director of the Oregon Brewers Festival and owner of public relations firm Crabbsoup. In this interview, she discusses her work as public relations manager of multiple beer-related accounts, emphasizing the advent of social media and the importance—and enjoyment—of forging local networks. Having been involved with the Oregon Brewers Festival for more than twenty years, Crabb offers insight regarding the organization and atmosphere of the popular event. Crabb also recounts the cultural climates of Portland and Eugene during her adolescent and collegiate years. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on June 2, 2016 at the City of Portland Archives and Records Management office.
  - Cox, Theodore, June 7, 2016
    Theodore “Ted” Cox is the founder and owner of the Old World Deli complex in Corvallis, Oregon, which houses the Oregon Trail Brewery and several galleries in addition to the restaurant. In this interview, Cox discusses the events which led him to open the deli, including two stints with the Peace Corps. Cox also covers his time as a student, teacher and volleyball coach at Oregon State University and Linn Benton Community College, where he studied and taught physical education. A regional history aficionado, Cox shares several stories and anecdotes about Corvallis and Prohibition-era brewing practices. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on June 7, 2016 at Cox’s home in Corvallis. This interview has also been described in the Oregon State University Sesquicentennial Oral History Collection (OH 026).
  - Hedgmon, Lee, June 9, 2016
    Lee Hedgmon is a Portland-based home and commercial brewer. She is active in the Oregon Brew Crew (serving as their first female president in 2015), Ladies of Lager Ales, and Pink Boots Society, working to increase the number of women in brewing. In addition to brewing, in this interview Hedgmon talks about growing up in Portland, her work as a youth activist, experiences as a student at PCC and PSU, activism in the queer community, involvement with JobCorp in Astoria, work in the hotel industry in Portland, and graduate work in the University of Minnesota Feminist Studies program. She shares stories on her early homebrewing adventures and experiences, as well as her transition to paid positions at Coalition Brewing, Portland U Brew, FA Steinbarts, Pints, and Groundbreaker. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on June 9, 2016 at The Valley Library in Corvallis.
  - Pullman, Mellie, June 17, 2016
    Dr. Mellie Pullman is a professor at Portland State University, where she is the Director of the Business of Craft Brewing Program. In this interview, Pullman talks about growing up in Chicago, traveling through the country and taking classes at The Evergreen State College before settling in Park City, Utah, where she became the first female brewmaster in the US at Schirf Brewing (1986). Pullman talks about what it was like to be a woman in male dominated industries, working at Cornell University, moving to Portland, and how her research focus shifted from food to beer. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on June 17, 2016 at Pullman’s home in Portland.
  - Engdahl, Emily, June 17, 2016
    Emily Engdahl is the Executive Director of The Pink Boots Society. In her interview, Engdahl talks about the importance of an educational and outreach organization such as Pink Boots for women working in the brewing industries, as well as about growing up in Portland, creating PDX Beer Geeks and Oregon Beer Country, and her work as an artist and graphic designer. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on June 17, 2016 at the McMenamins Mission Theater in Portland.
  - Baldwin, Natalie, June 17, 2016
    Natalie Baldwin, brewer at Burnside Brewing, talks about growing up in Vail, Colorado, moving to Portland, and learning about brewing. Baldwin is known for pushing the boundaries of classic styles, and she addresses how her mentors in brewing have encouraged her experimentation. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on June 17, 2016 at the McMenamins Mission Theater in Portland.
  - Leikam, Sonia Marie, June 17, 2016
    Sonia Marie Leikam owns Leikam Brewing with her husband, but also works full-time at the Oregon Jewish Community Foundation. In her interview, Leikam talks about growing up in the Bay Area, moving to Portland to attend Lewis & Clark College, the evolution of her Jewish faith, teaching in Portland area schools, starting the brewery (Community Supported Brewery, Kosher certified), balancing work and family, and her work as an educator and human rights advocate. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on June 17, 2016 at the McMenamins Mission Theater in Portland.
  - Kent, Jennifer, July 7, 2016
    ​Jennifer Kent is the brewer at the McMenamins Thompson Brewery & Public House. In her interview, Kent talks about her early childhood in Alaska and Colorado; memories of growing up in Newport, Oregon; her family and mother's art career; work in the food service industry; her career at McMenamins as a brewer; the art of brewing and brewing community in the region; and being a woman in a male dominated brewing industry. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on July 7, 2016 at the McMenamins Thompson Brewery & Public House in Salem, Oregon.
  - Smith, Blair, October 5, 2016
    Blair Smith is the owner, orchardist, and cider-maker for Apple Outlaw. In his interview, Smith talks about growing up in Stockton, CA and his work as a software engineer in Livermore; moving to rural Oregon and learning about running an organic orchard; and the transition from non-alcoholic to hard cider. More generally, Blair talks about how his family has focused on community involvement and environmental responsibility. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on October 5, 2016 at Apple Outlaw in Applegate, Oregon. Also present was Maureen Battistella, who works to document the Southern Oregon wine industry.
  - Seghetti, Guy, October 6, 2016
    Guy Seghetti worked as a USDA Hops and Essential Oils lab and agricultural technician at OSU from 1968-1977. In his interview, Seghetti talks about growing up in Corvallis, his time at University of Utah while pursuing a degree in Anthropology, and his experiences as a technician in Corvallis. Specifically, Seghetti provides personal observation about the breeding program, with anecdotes and details about this crucial time in hops history with the release of the Cascade and other hops in the 1970s. Seghetti left the program in 1977 to teach Social Science for Roseburg, Oregon, public schools; he retired in 2008. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on October 6, 2016 in Roseburg, Oregon.
  - Allen, Lisa, October 20, 2016
    Lisa Allen is a brewer at Heater Allen Brewing in McMinnville. In her interview, Allen discusses growing up in Tualatin; her junior year spent in Moraga, California; her experiences at OSU in the early 2000s, and her travels to New Zealand. After graduating, Allen worked in the wine industry, starting with harvest and then working in tasting rooms. In 2009, Allen left the wine industry to join her father at Heater Allen Brewing, which he'd opened in 2007 after a long career as an investment banker; Rick Allen joins the interview at the end to discuss the origins and operations of the brewery, especially their choice to focus on German lagers and pilsners. Allen also discusses her experiences as a woman in the brewing industry, as well as what it is like to brew in the middle of Oregon's wine country. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on October 20, 2016 in McMinnville, Oregon.
  - Pedersen, Sarah, October 20, 2016
    Sarah Pederson is the owner of Saravesa, a bar, bottle shop, and breweriana showroom in North Portland. In this interview she discusses growing up in a small town in Wisconsin, going to college in Minneapolis, living and working in Los Angeles, and moving to Portland. Pederson shares stories of her work doing Public Relations for a High Tech firm and working for her friend at the patisserie and bar Pix, as well as education at the American Brewer's Guild, early jobs at the breweries Hair of the Dog and the New Old Lompoc Bar, and opening of Saravesa in 2008. At the end of the interview, Pederson talks about being a woman working in a male dominated industry. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on October 20, 2016 in Portland, Oregon.
  - Almlie, Kyle, October 27, 2016
    Kyle Almlie is a graduate teaching assistant in the chemistry department of Oregon State University, as well as a home brewer. In this interview, he compares living in Corvallis to growing up in Chico, California, his growing knowledge and passion for both teaching and chemistry, and the challenges of participating in beer and homebrew culture while also being gluten-free. Kyle also discusses the chemistry behind brewing gluten-free beers and different kinds of mead, the chemistry of alpha acids in hops, and how that all ties back into his experience as an analytical chemist. This past spring, Kyle won awards both for his work as a TA and for a poster about his work developing equipment for fluorescence spectroscopy in the Sean Burrows, and he also reflects on those experiences. The interview was conducted by Gillian Bergmann on October 27, 2016 in the Valley Library in Corvallis. Also present was Tiah Edmunson-Morton, director of the Oregon Hops and Brewing Archives.
  - Allen, Rick, November 16, 2016
    Rick Allen is the owner and head brewer at Heater Allen. In his interview, Allen shares stories about his family's deep roots at OSU, dating to his grandmother and grandfather's time OAC in the 1910s and daughter's graduation in the 2000s. He also discusses his time as a student at OSU in the early 1970s, including the campus climate, student perspective on the administration, and campus traditions linked to his fraternity (Beta Theta Pi). After university, Allen took a position as an investment banker in Portland, with short moves to Washington and California for employment; he left that field in the early 2000s. An avid home brewer, Allen considered a second career as a vintner, but decided to open a brewery in 2007 in McMinnville, Oregon. In the latter part of his interview, Allen discusses the important influences on his brewing style, experiences operating a brewery in Oregon's wine country, and issues facing small breweries in 2016. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on November 16, 2016 in McMinnville, Oregon.
- Interviews, 2017; Series 4
  - Norton, Don, January 18, 2017
    Don Norton is the owner of Norton Hop Farm, a small organic hop farm established in Goshen, Oregon in 2008. In his interview, Norton talks about growing up in the Eugene area, experiences installing and running his 1-acre farm, and work with an herbal supply company. Norton also addresses some of his concerns as a small grower, including outlets for selling his product and expansion. This interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton and Michelle McKay in Bend, Oregon at the Hop Growers of America Conference on January 18, 2017.
  - Crosby, Brian, January 18, 2017
    Brian Crosby is a fourth generation Crosby hop family member, and works as an accounts manager. In his interview, Crosby talks extensively about the family farm and relationships, including how he learned about farm operations and the impact of mechanization on the industry. He also discusses more current topics, such as the shift towards Salmon-Safe Certified farming practices and innovative processing techniques. Crosby served in the US Navy, retuning from service to attend Oregon State University 1984-1988, receiving his BS in Civil Engineering and playing in the the Oregon State Rugby Club while in school. He was a commercial construction manager before returning to the farm business. This interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton and Michelle McKay in Bend, Oregon at the Hop Growers of America Conference on January 18, 2017.
  - Gillson, Cheryl, January 19, 2017
    Cheryl Gillson works as a marketing and manager at Rogue Farms in Independence, Oregon. In her interview, Gillson talks about growing up in California, working as Jack Joyce's assistant at Rogue Ales & Spirits, traveling and living abroad, and returning to Rogue to work on their farm in Independence as a "beer farmer." She talks extensively about the crops they grow, and the impact learning about farming has had on her life. This interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton and Michelle McKay in Bend, Oregon at the Hop Growers of America Conference on January 19, 2017.
  - Shellhammer, Thomas, February 14, 2017
    Dr. Thomas Shellhammer is the Nor’Wester Professor of Fermentation Science and is an internationally recognized expert in hops chemistry. In this interview he talks about growing up in San Jose, early memories of his father's work as a field biologist studying fire ecology and his mother's work as an arts educator, and his early interest in the sciences. He also discusses his food and fermentation sciences education at UC Davis, internships or work experiences during his path from BS to PhD, and early impressions of Oregon State's Food and Fermentation program. Shellhammer also discusses topics such as the demographics of the industries over time, as well as his observations of the industry's patterns of growth and contraction. This interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton at Weigand Hall on OSU's campus on February 14, 2017.
  - Larsen, Lee, February 20, 2017